L pi is a contraction and it is others may
leave if they want to
the guys who would not actually revised last
week's lecture if you are so interested or
so disinterested you could leave right so
just teach for the six people could read okay
I do not care right so there is one question
last class to show that this actually works
we need to show that we say V is a banach
space okay how hard is it to show that V is
a banach space what is V what is v V what
is the space V we want to show as a barrack
space of all value functions okay.
value functions is little tricky because value
functions means that there is some policy
or something that generates that right need
that need not necessarily be true it is very
hard to quantify it such a space right so
V is a space of all functions that satisfy
something for us what is that very simple
what is the most basic condition we put
right so component wise the function is bounded
see so think of an element here right and
then I take V os s which is one component
of the vector V like that component will be
always bounded right.
Okay and think of what is the norm that we
are considering here in this space so essentially
what capital V is it is a space of all bounded
what functions right the space of all bounded
functions right so because we have this function
operating on a discrete space right so we
can just think of this as points in space
right but it is actually is a function space
is actually space of functions right so V
is a space of bounded functions right and
what is the norm that we consider max norm
right the max now right and what is it that
we need to show if it is a banach space it
converges right but what we know here all
Cauchy sequences what does the Cauchy sequence
say as you keep growing difference becomes
smaller and smaller and smaller so what does
that mean it converges it should be in the
same space right.
So what can you tell me about any such space
with the max norm on it so it is a complete
it is a full space right I am not excluding
anything the only problem I have is that my
functions have to be component wise bounded
right the functions have to be component wise
bounded right and if you look at the right
so essentially the idea is that since I am
assuming that my functions are getting epsilon
close to each other my vectors are getting
epsilon close to each other and given the
fact that their component wise they are all
bounded right.
So the limit also has to be a bounded function
and as long as it is a bounded function it
will exist in this space so the easier thing
to show is RM is bounded under the euclidean
norms right under the max norm so RN is bounded
under any now okay so the tricky part is this
is not RN it is a subset of RN right why is
it a subset of RN v and they say all components
have to be bounded right so RN does not have
that restriction I could have some components
that can grow unbounded right.
So the only tricky part here is so that okay
since I am talking about bounded vectors okay
the point is the limit of this bounded vector
should also be bounded is actually not always
the case right I mean I can actually set up
space set up situations where I'm considering
bound identities but the limit of the bound
identities happens to be at set up a sequence
where I am considering only bound identities
and but the limit of the boundary identities
happens to be something that is unbounded
right but in this case I am not setting up
any kind of a generic sequence like this right
so I am actually setting up a sequence of
bounded function so the sequence eventually
has to be bounded.
So it is little tricky to show that but the
intuition is that it is going to be a set
of sequence of bounded functions and I am
assuming that the difference between them
is becoming smaller and smaller and sway infinitely
smaller right as it becomes larger and larger
and therefore you cannot have an unbounded
value that is infinitely close to a bounded
value so therefore we assume that it is finally
the limit exists in V so I am not doing a
formal proof for it because it involves introducing
more concepts but the intuition is there.
So next we have to move on to the optimality
equation right
you know the Bellman optimality equation oh
we introduce all these notations so we talked
about this right marginalizing over s' did
we introduce the notation last class
right so this is essentially the expected
value of the reward given the state and the
action right I am marginalizing over a s'
so basically summing over the probability
of seeing all possible s' and this we spoke
about right and yeah so this is this is the
optimality equation right.
So what we are doing to go from here to here
right is writing this in a vector notation
right so translating all of this into vector
notation is if remember I defined R pi as
the expected value will get following pi right
for the next immediate step right so where
so the only difference here is here I assume
that you use a here at but here I am assuming
you are using a pi okay and so this is the
probability of that of the next state following
policy pi right here again I am assuming a
here I am assuming pi and here I am saying
v star of j and here I am saying v star the
summation is gone.
Vp no so I will tell you why right so I am
doing max over a right so for each state I
get one max or a so I will get 1 action as
the max action let us say let us assume that
there is one action as the max action for
each yes right so what essentially this is
give me it gives me a mapping from state to
action so what is that mapping it is a policy
so that is a policy pi we are talking about
here right this is essentially a component
wise maximization of this expression so for
every state I will write out this expression
for every state I will find the a that correspondingly
maximizes that expression.
Let us just like it I there right so every
state I will solve this thing I will find
out what that is I can set that as the max
by right so this max here is a cut for saying
it is a component wise max right for every
S I learn this max independently I could afford
to do I am not making any assumptions about
the structure of the policy pi right so for
every state I can set an arbitrary action
as the action for p right.
So this is my well-being optimality equation
return in vector form right makes sense it
is so now I am going to define this as an
operator.
So I am going to define L as that operator
that takes in V star and does this computation
okay and gives you back another point in the
space let L is an operator so L is essentially
so LV and what we are claiming is that V star
is the fixed point of L right so last class
we looked at L pi right which was the iterative
process for valve an equation for V pi now
this is a bellman equation for V star so I
have written it like this right and then taken
this whole operation and converted that into
a single matrix operation right and so now
the function essentially becomes LV is this.
Say L is a not a linear function of V because
of the max it is L is not a linear function
of wave just for convenience I am writing
it as LV it looks like it is a matrix multiplication
it is not okay and that is basically the claim
here is that what is the clam L is a contraction
so if I say L is a contraction what do you
get you get lots of things for free right
so what do you do what do you get if L is
a contraction in kind of hand waving we argued
that V is a banach space L is a contraction
so what do you get a that is a unique fixed
point V star right.
And if you do it iterative it converges to
v star okay so it starts from some arbitrary
V or repeatedly apply a L it converges to
v star so we got both this thing for free
so let us look at showing this right so when
they say a stars it means that the best action
to do at least one of the best actions to
do in state s.
Remember we talked about the world they could
go in any combination so you could reach the
top right necessarily so it could go either
right or you could go up any combination of
right and up will work to get you to the final
state right so either both right and up where
the best actions it could be more than one
best action both of this do not preclude multiple
things being best okay and this is just finding
out the value corresponding to the best action
right I am not so we argued that earlier also
there could be multiple best actions but there
will be only one value corresponding to those
best actions.
Regardless of whether we go up where you go
right you will take the same number of steps
to reach the goal right so the value will
be the same but you could have multiple policies
so I'm not procuring this any one of those
next a you plug in here right let us likewise
any one of the best p you plug in here and
re compute v star so I am not saying you have
to find one pi or anything right so this here
I am picking one such a that is why I did
not say a is equal to a star is equal to R
max I am saying a star belongs to our max
okay.
So what we really have to establish is that
later on which will be useful for you in your
doing the assignment is that you do not really
have to consider probability stochastic policies
when you are doing dealing with MDPs at least
you do not have to consider sarcastic policies
for finite MDPs there will always be a deterministic
optimal policy so it is enough if you only
search for one deterministic policy you do
not have to search for stochastic policies
that will have to show right what I will do
is I will not do it in class so I will give
you a small right up to read so from my notes
I will make up right up and put it online
so you can read it from so this just to convince
you that is a little bit of algebra not too
much right.
So just to convince you that deterministic
policies are sufficient okay but right now
so far I have not assumed anything like that
and this assuming that is one action that
is the best right
and let us assume that I have
two functions V and U okay and I have L operating
on V and L operating on U remember from our
discussion in the last class that Lvof s is
a function L of v is a function LV of s is
the sth of that component of that function
or LV acting on s whatever is the output okay
so the function is LV L is not operating on
VS I think a lot of you had a confusion last
class L is not operating on V of s L is something
that takes a function as an argument and outputs
a function right so LV is the function right
you take V you apply L on it and then the
resulting function you apply on S right.
So likewise U take you apply L on it and the
resulting function you apply on S okay so
I am first making the assumption that LV of
s is greater than LU of s okay so what do
I need to show come closer than VS and US
that is basic to order remember we did this
last class also we did the same thing so we
assumed one way we showed it and then we flip
the other way showed it and then we showed
that for every state s the absolute value
in contracted that for the norm will also
contract exactly.
The same thing that we did last class that
is why I asked people to revise from the last
class and come so that I can just go through
this very easily right and this clarifying
this because last class after the class a
lot of people are asking me questions about
this LVLU business so that is clear right
so LV is a function which is operating on
S okay
right so a star is the one that gives you
the max right so that gives you the max here
so I remove the max and wrote it in terms
of a star right so this is essentially a L
of v okay.
So I put a less than or equal to here so I
am going to do something on the other term
which L of u okay so if I am going to expand
I L of uI might as L equal to right so I am
going to do something tricky with the other
term so what is it tricky things Tricky thing
I did I got rid of the max here also but instead
of using the max corresponding to you Uj I
am using the max corresponding to V right
so a star is what is a max when V is the function
here right a star is the max and V is the
function here but I am plugging in a star
itself here right.
So what can you tell me about this it will
be less than the actual max when L operates
on U see that so when the L is operating on
this right so essentially there is a max over
here and there will be U here right but instead
of taking the max action I am taking some
arbitrary action which is a star and they
plugging it in there for this will be less
than the max right there for this difference
will be greater than this because this in
this term this is also the max corresponding
to V and this will be the max corresponding
to U right so I am taking the difference but
now what I have done is have replaced this
term with something that smaller therefore
this will be greater this difference will
be greater okay.
Is it clear V is not optimal but a star is
optimal for V when I am doing that maxing
maximizing thing here right so a star is the
solution for this maximizing this optimization
this is an optimization problem right so I
am doing our max over a so as a star is one
of the solutions for solving this problem
when the function here is V it may or may
not be the solution when the function is U
so if it is the solution then this will be
inequality if it is not a solution then this
will be lesser than okay great.
So now the advantage of doing this we can
start canceling out some terms and try to
make this simpler so what will you end up
with is.
So this term is equal to there is a same trick
that we did last right so this is component-wise
difference it will be bounded by the max difference
which is the norm right and once I write it
as the norm it becomes independent of J so
I can take that out and they have this summation
and the summation is 1 right so what do I
have here so I have so I can do the same thing
I can flip things around right I can start
with 0 less than or equal to LU minus LV right
and then pick the action that maximizes the
right-hand side for U and then do the whole
thing right I will get exactly the same thing.
So showing the other way round also right
so I finally get that okay so now this gives
us a way of solving the solving in MDP.
How do I do that start with an arbitrary value
function just keep applying L repeatedly I
will end up with an optimal value function
so once I have an optimal value function how
will I recover an optimal policy I can do
this essentially what I did here run this
on V star right this will give me an optimal
policy then I can pick any action in the arbitrary
action from that from the R max and take that
as may optimal action or I could just define
some kind of a probability distribution over
that take the dress off Matt great so we will
just write that down so this is a very popular
algorithm called
value iteration because you start with the
value and then you iterate over it until you
come to the final conversion value right.
So this is yeah so for people who are wondering
about their programming assignment herd management
assignment so value iteration is one of the
things I am asking you to do right so you
just start with an arbitrary value function
later then repeatedly implement L and run
it until you come to a fixed point the only
interesting thing now here is what is the
what is what how many more times do you have
to say arbitrary what is the more interesting
point is we have talked about one end I said
it is not the right answer.
When do I stop and wait not the number but
when do I stop it cannot be a simple number
I just cannot say run a thousand times okay
so I should have some other convergent test
that tells me when it has topped right essentially
I keep doing it until successive iterates
or within a few are same you are a great event
but same will not happen same will take forever
very close let us listen ah but then you are
not computing the policy every time right
the policy itself a painful process you have
to be greedy with respect to the value function.
So every time if every iteration you are computing
the same policy it becomes a problem we are
going to compute the policy in every iteration
then it might be a problem because you have
to do an additional computation maybe not
I mean it is a call that you have to make
but if you want to give certain guarantees
about what will hold when things converge
then you better have a bound on the value
function okay.
So we will come to another algorithm called
policy iteration where we can work with the
space of policies okay but right now I am
just going to do this with value functions
right yeah so select some v elelment of V
pick an epsilon for our stopping criterion
and start your iteration another just a little
component-wise have written your VN+ 1 =VVN+
1= LVN is basically what I am asking you to
do here right.
So this is nothing okay so the interesting
part is this.
Is fine all of this is fine the only tricky
thing is why do you have this weird expression
here why not just epsilon why do you have
epsilon into i minus gamma upon 2 gamma so
I am doing value iteration what I am I computing
what I am interested in computing what do
I expect output at the end of V star or pi
star or whatever it I'm expecting to output
V star right but my stopping condition is
V and V n plus 1 right but I would like to
give you guarantees on how far away I am from
V star at the end of the day not necessarily
how close V n and V n plus 1 are right so
we will take this close class condition and
convert it into a guarantee on how close you
are to be V star and then when we do that
conversion we will find that you will be what
do you think you will be guess guys I mean
you should be able to guess by now what do
you think will be epsilon close to V star
okay.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resource Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights Reserved